Guide to the Sylvanus Dyer Locke Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sylvanus Dyer Locke papers
1859-1942
MS 327
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
The papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, patents, and printed material which relate to Sylvanus Dyer Locke's patented self-binding harvester and other inventions. Correspondents include attorneys, patent solicitors, and other manufacturers of farm equipment and heavy machinery. Some materials also relate to Sylvanus D. Locke, Jr. and the Locke Steel Chain Company of Bridgeport, Connecticut. The addition to the papers contains family correspondence, photographs, and academic reports of the Locke children as well as materials relating to the family business.
Locke, Sylvanus Dyer, 1833-1896
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1964. Gift of National Museum of American History, 1998.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Letterpress Copybooks, 1877-1893. II. General Correspondence, 1875-1917. III. Topical Files, 1859-1942.
Scope and Contents
The Sylvanus Dyer Locke Papers consist of correspondence, letterbooks, patents, and printed material which document the last twenty years of Sylvanus D. Locke's life in Hoosick Falls, New York, and relate primarily to his inventions, particularly his self-binding harvester and his detachable steel link belting. Correspondents include attorneys, patent examiners and solicitors, and other manufacturers of farm equipment and heavy machinery. Some material also concerns Sylvanus D. Locke, Jr. and the Locke Steel Chain Company of Bridgeport, Connecticut.
The papers, which the Yale Library purchased in 1964, are arranged in three series:
I. LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS, 1877-1893
II. GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1875-1917
III. TOPICAL FILES, 1859-1942
The papers date from 1859 to 1942 but the bulk of the material is business correspondence of Sylvanus Locke from 1876 to 1896.
Series I contains nine volumes of Sylvanus Locke's "private" letterbooks, which include both outgoing business and family letters dating from 1877 to 1893. The letters begin several years after Locke had secured a patent for his automatic reaper and binder. Business correspondence focuses on the protection of this patent from infringement by manufacturers of farm machinery such as the H.M. McCormick Company. Correspondents include patent examiners and solicitors such as J.G. Parkinson. Some correspondence concerns Locke's other inventions. There are also letters to Locke's brothers, wife, and children and letters concerning domestic bills, medical treatments and expenses, and the children's education. Indexes in the letterpress volumes serve as a guide to correspondents in both Series I and II.
Series II contains Locke's incoming correspondence from 1876 to 1877 and from 1887 to 1896. Correspondents and subjects included in Series II are similar to those in Series I. Many incoming letters filed under 'L' relate to the Locke family. For the years 1893 to 1896 the series also includes copies of Locke's outgoing letters. Correspondence after 1896 relates to Sylvanus Locke, Jr. and the Locke Steel Belt Company. This correspondence is, however, fragmentary. Series II also contains numerous bills and receipts of the Locke family. At the end of the series are several folders of similar correspondence which is unarranged and marked "Miscellaneous." The series concludes with two boxes of incoming and outgoing telegrams mounted in volumes.
Series III is composed of printed material, photographs, and memorabilia, the majority of which relates to Sylvanus Locke and his inventions. The largest quantity of material is in the folders "Patents," which contain printed copies of Locke's patents for his inventions as well as patents of others for similar devices. The printed material includes advertising circulars, sales catalogues, and price lists for harvesting machinery. Also in these folders are printed legal documents relating to patent litigation in Locke's behalf and writings by Locke including a description of his automatic car coupler. An address delivered by Locke before the New York State Assembly (folder 176) is one of the few documents in the papers relating to Locke's term in the New York legislature.
Biographical / Historical
Sylvanus Dyer Locke was born in Otsego County, New York on September 11, 1833. In 1870, while working for the Walter A. Wood Mowing and Reaping Machine Company of Hoosick Falls, New York, Locke succeeded in building an automatic reaper and binder. Locke served one term in the New York state legislature (1883-1885). He was also the inventor of a train car coupling device and a machine for manufacturing detachable steel link belting. Locke died in 1896.
Agricultural machinery; Business; Harvesting machinery; Patents -- United States; Hoosick Falls (N.Y.); Patents (license); Inventors; Manufacturers; Locke, Sylvanus Dyer, 1833-1896; Locke, Sylvanus Dyer, 1871-; Locke Steel Chain Company
- LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS, 1877-1893; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged chronologically by volume. Each volume contains an alphabetical index of correspondents.
  - 1877-1882 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - 1883-1889 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - 1889-1893 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1875-1917; Series II
  The series is arranged in alphabetical divisions. Within each division the correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - A, 1887-1916 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
  - B, 1876-1917 (Box 4, Folder 14-19)
  - C, 1876-1913, undated (Box 4, Folder 20-26)
  - D, 1876-1915 (Box 5, Folder 27-30)
  - E, 1876-1916 (Box 5, Folder 31-34)
  - F, 1876-1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
  - G, 1876-1916 (Box 5, Folder 37-39)
  - H, 1876-1913, undated (Box 5, Folder 40-48)
  - I, 1888-1916 (Box 6, Folder 49-51)
  - J, 1876-1911 (Box 6, Folder 52-53)
  - K, 1876-1916 (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
  - L, 1876-1916, undated (Box 6, Folder 56-69)
  - M, 1876-1916 (Box 7, Folder 70-76)
  - N, 1879-1916 (Box 7, Folder 77-80)
  - 0, 1887-1915 (Box 7, Folder 81-83)
  - P, 1876-1891 (Box 7, Folder 84-88)
  - P, 1893-1916, undated (Box 8, Folder 89-97)
  - Q, 1888-1897 (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - R, 1876-1908 (Box 8, Folder 99-104)
  - S, 1876-1879 (Box 8, Folder 105-108)
  - S, 1887-1916, undated (Box 9, Folder 109-118)
  - T, 1877-1915, undated (Box 9, Folder 119-123)
  - U, 1893-1916 (Box 9, Folder 124-125)
  - V, 1877-1894 (Box 9, Folder 126-127)
  - V, 1895-1897 (Box 10, Folder 128-130)
  - W, 1875-1912, undated (Box 10, Folder 131-142)
  - Y, 1877-1913 (Box 10, Folder 143)
  - Miscellaneous, 1875-1888 (Box 10, Folder 144-146)
  - Miscellaneous, 1889-1910 (Box 11, Folder 147-154)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 11, Folder 155)
  - Telegrams, 1871-1886 (Box 12, Folder 156-170)
  - Telegrams, 1886-1887 (Box 13, Folder 171-175)
- TOPICAL FILES, 1859-1942; Series III
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by record type.
  - Address before the New York State Assembly, 1884 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - Bar certificate, 1861 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - Clippings, 1887, 1896, undated (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - Examination, 1891 (Box 14, Folder 179)
  - Genealogy, undated (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - Patents, 1859-1901 (Box 14, Folder 181-199)
  - No folder (Box 14, Folder 200)
  - Patents, 1873, 1881 (Box 15, Folder 201-202)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 15, Folder 203-204)
  - Printed material, 1873-1891 (Box 15, Folder 205-213)
  - Printed material, 1892-1942, undated (Box 16, Folder 214-219)
  - Transactions, financial [ledger, daybook], 1877-1880 (Box 17, Folder 220-221)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-049
  The accession is comprised of correspondence, photographs, and report cards relating to Sylvanus Dyer Locke's work, and his family, in Hoosick Falls, New York between 1876 and 1896. The bulk of the material dates from 1888 to 1893. The papers illustrate both the business interests of Locke and his family responsibilities, especially concerning the education and conduct of his three children. They also relate to Sylvanus Locke Jr. and the Locke Steel Belt Company of Bridgeport, Connecticut.
  - Automatic Binding Harvester Company
    - 1872-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1894-1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Purchase of cyprus trees, Florida, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Drive chains, patent, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Locke Steel Belt Company, 1899-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sylvanus D. Locke, Jr
    - Photograph, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence [with father], 1886-1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Report cards, 1887-1888 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - John Parker Locke
    - Correspondence [with father], 1888-1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Report cards, 1887-1888 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lilla Locke
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence [with father], 1890 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Report cards, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Sylvanus D. Locke [correspondence with husband], 1893-1898 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sylvanus D. Locke [correspondence with brothers], 1888-1893 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Family bills, 1892-1900 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Family correspondence [miscellaenous], 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 20)